Guide to the Irving S. Olds Collection of Naval and Other Historical Prints and Related Papers 1587-1960 PR 47
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Prints & Related Papers from the Original Olds Donation, 1587-1960, undated; 17.63 Linear feet in 33 flat file folders and 6 boxes
  - Subseries I.A. Prints and Other Documents from the Olds Collection, 1587-1921, undated; 16 Linear feet in flat files and three boxes
    - Print No. 937. Aquatint: "Plate 1. Situation of His Majesty's Frigate Java, Captain Lambert,...", 1814 (Folder FF-17)
      Full title: "Plate 1. Situation of His Majesty's Frigate Java, Captain Lambert, at 5 Min. past 3 P.M. after an hours close & severe Action with the American Frigate Constitution, in which she was so much disabled in her Masts, Sails, & Rigging, by the Enemy's very superior Force & Weight of Metal, that in the attempt to Board, with every prospect of success, her Foremast fell, & she was rendered totally unmanageable." Drawn & etched by N. Pocock from a sketch by Lieut. Buchanan. Engraved by R. & D. Havell. Published January 1, 1814 by Boydell & Co., London. One of a set of four prints, (see print nos. 937-940), of the engagement between the Constitution and the Java on December 29, 1812. See print no. 181 for earlier state. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 938. Aquatint: "Plate 2nd. The Java, as she appeared at 35 Min. past 4 P.M. ...", 1814 (Folder FF-23)
      Full title: "Plate 2nd. The Java, as she appeared at 35 Min. past 4 P.M. after having sustained several raking Broadsides from the Constitution whilst closely engageing her, until she became a perfect Wreck…" Drawn & etched by N. Pocock from a sketch by Lieut. Buchanan. Engraved by R. & D. Havell. Published January 1, 1814 by Boydell & Co., London. One of a set of four prints.(see print nos. 937-940), of the engagement between the Constitution and the Java on December 29, 1812. See print no. 182 for earlier state. Hand colored.
    - Print No. 939. Aquatint: "Plate 3d. The Java totally dismasted ...", 1814 (Folder FF-23)
      Full title: "Plate 3rd. The Java totally dismasted endeavouring to Wear by the assistance of a Jury Staysail hhoisted to the Stump of the Foremast & Bowsprit; the Constitution Crossing her Bow in a Raking Position, Compels her to Surrender at 50 Min. past 5." Drawn & etched by N. Pocock from a sketch by Leiut. Buchanan. Engraved by R. & D. Havell. Published January 1, 1814 by Boydell & Co., London. One of a set of four prints. (see print nos. 937-940), of the engagement between the Constitution and the Java on December 29, 1812. See print no. 183 for earlier state. Hand colored.
    - Print No. 940. Aquatint: "Plate 4th. The Java in a Sinking state, set fire to, & Blowing up…", 1814 (Folder FF-23)
      Full title: "Plate 4th. The Java in a Sinking state, set fire to, & Blowing up. The Constitution at a distance a head. Laying to unbending Sails, repairing her Rigging etc. on the Evening of 29th Dec. 1812. Drawn & etched by N. Pocock from a sketch by Lieut. Buchanan. Engraved by R. & D. Havell. Published January 1, 1814 by Boydell & Co., London. One of a set of four prints (see print nos. 937-940) of the engagement between the Constitution and the Java on December 29, 1812. See print no. 184 for earlier state. Hand colored.
    - Olds Catalogue. Supplement 2. (Folder -)
    - Print No. 944. Mezzotint portrait: "Iohn Paul Iones", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Attributed to Richard Brookshaw. Portrait of John Paul Jones, Commander of a Squadron in the service of Thirteen States of North America. [London, 1779]. Proof before letters of portrait of Jones. The prototype of subsequent similar engraved likenesses of Jones published abroad. See Print No. 457.
    - Print No. 945. Engraved map, colored: "A Plan of New York Island...", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Full title: "A Plan of New York Island, part of Long Island &ce. showing the Position of the American and British Armies, before, at, and after the engagement on the Heights, August 27th 1776." At top: "Engraved for Washingtons Life" "Plate II." Drawn by S. Lewis. J.H. Seymour sculp. Published in Philadelphia by C.P. Wayne.
    - Print No. 947. Engraving: "Der Siegende Engeländer und der Streitende Americaner.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Engraving with German caption. "I.M.P. sc." "I.M. Probst. exc: av." Contemporary engraving in black & white of naval action off Mud Fort in Delaware River in October 1777.
    - Print No. 949. Lithograph, colored: "Episode de la Guerre de l'Indépendance.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Above title is "13." Drawn and lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Printed by Lemercier. Published by V. Delarue et Cie, Paris, Place du Louvre 10. Bottom right corner: "Leipzie bei Gebrûdor Rocca". Possibly a different state of Print No. 85.
    - Print No. 951. Engraving, colored: "Fregate des Etats unis d'Amérique faisant sécher ses hamacs.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Dessiné et Gravé par Baugean. Depicts American ship drying its nettings.
    - Print No. 952. Engraving, colored: "Pilote-Bot, petit Bâtiment des Etats-unis, au plus près … Bateau d'Amérique.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Dessiné et Gravé par Baugean.
    - Print No. 953. Lithograph, colored: "Pirate Attaqué Par Un Navire De Guerre.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      In top right corner: "No. 33". Drawn by Ferd. Perrot. Published by Victor Delarue, Paris. Lithographed by Rigo Freres et Cie.
    - Print No. 954. Engraving, colored: "Reddition de l'Armée angloises...", undated (Folder FF-17)
      Full title: "Reddition de l'Armée angloises commandée par Mylord Comte de Cornwallis aux Armees combinées des Etats unis de l'Amerique et de France aux orders des Generaux Washington et de Rochambeau a Yorck touwn et Glocester dans la Virginie, le 19 Octobre 1781." A Paris chez Mondhare.
    - Print No. 958. Lithograph, colored: "Bass Fishing at Macomb's Dam Harlem River, N.Y.", 1852 (Folder FF-18)
      From Nature and on Stone by F.F. Palmer. Lithographed and published by N. Currier, New York. First state. Peters no. 3225.
    - Print No. 962. Engraving, colored: "Combat Mémorable donné le. 7bre. 1779,...", undated (Folder FF-18)
      Full title: "Combat Mémorable donné le. 7bre. 1779, entre le Capitaine Pearson commandant le Sérapis, et Paul Jones commandant le Bon-Homme-Richard et son Escadre." A Paris chez Esnauts et Rapilly, rue St. Jacques a la Ville de Coutances. Statistics of the battle below the picture. Duplicate of Print No. 78, except in colors.
    - Print Nos. 968-973. Various items related to the Battle of Yorktown framed together, 1781?-1881 (Folder FF-18)
      Items removed from frame in September 2022 by conservator Alan Balicki.
      No. 968. "A representation of the sea fight, on the 5th of Sepr 1781, between Rear Admiral Graves & the Count de Grasse [Yorktown]" No engraver named, undated.
      No. 969. Woodcut "Yorktown--the engagement between the French and English fleets off Cape Henry, September 5, 1781." By J.O. Davidson. Colored by Evelyn Olds. from Harper's Weekly of October 22, 1881.
      No. 970. Engraving. "Reddition de l'Armee du Lord Cornwallis..." [1781?]
      No. 971. Engraving. Portrait of Count de Grasse, by Miller, W. Agus, sculpt. [1782].
      No. 972. Engraving. Lafayette. Small, circular.
      No. 973. Engraving. Washington. Small, circular.
    - Print No. 974. Engraving, small circular: "Essex & Alert. Aug. 13, 1812.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Small circular engraving of the two ships, The Essex and The Alert. Illustration is from Gilbert J. Hunt's History of the Late War, N.Y., 1819. Companion to a circular portrait of David Porter (Print No. 830), published by Ch. Bance, Paris.
    - Print No. 975. The Shannon Frigate, Capt Burke, Boarding & Capturing the American Frigate, Chesapeake, off Boston, June 1st, 1813 in Fifteen Minutes, undated (Box 9)
      In frame and old glass. Color. Printed by W.B. Walker, London.
    - Print No. 976. The Pelican Sloop of War, Cap Maples, Rakeing & Capturing the American Brig Argus, on the 14 of Augt 1813, after an Action of 40 Minutes..., undated (Box 9)
    - Print No. 978. Aquatint: "The Patriot exalted.", 1792 (Folder FF-27)
      Designed by James Sayers. "J.S.f." "Published 15th March 1792 by Thos Cornell Bruton Street." "'Catherine II places in its niche the bust of Fox...A bust of Paul Jones...[looks] up at Fox with a sinister glare.' British Museum, Caricaturues, 8067."
    - Print No. 981. Engraving: "A NWbN View of Charles Town from on board the Bristol Commodore Sir Peter Parker Knt. &tc &tc...", 1776 (Folder FF-27)
      Full title: "A NWbN View of Charles Town from on board the Bristol Commodore Sir Peter Parker Knt. &tc &tc taken in Five Fathom Hole the day after the Attack upon Fort Sullivan by the Commodore & his Squadron, which action continued 9 hours, 40 minutes." Engraved and published in London by Wm. Faden Corner of St. Martins Lane Charing Cross on Augt. 10th 1776. Key to view is below title. "To Commodore Sir Peter Parker Knt. etc. etc. etc. This view is most humbly Dedicated and Presented by Lt. Colonel Thos. James R.R. of Artillery, Five Fathom Hole South Carolina, June 29th 1776.
    - Print No. 982. Engraved map entitled: "A Sketch of the Operations before Charleston the Capital of South Carolina.", 1780 (Folder FF-18)
      Published June 17, 1780 by J.F.W. Des Barres. Artist, engraver and publisher not named. Fortifications and locations of British and American forces, and warships included. Inset map of Charleston Harbor.
    - Print No. 984. Engraved map: "The Taking of Cape Breton, the 14th of Iune, 1745.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      No publisher, engraver, or date is given. (Capt. M. fecit) Below the map depicting "The Isle of Cape Breton" is a key to the battle.
    - Print No. 985. Engraving: "The Expedition against Cape Breton in Nova Scotia, 1745.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      No publisher, engraver, or date is given. Explanation below title is as follows,: "Cape Breton with the Imperial Fort of Louisbourg was taken (after siege of 40 days)by the New England Forces under the Command of the Honble. William Pepperel Esqr. & a squadron of his Majesty's Ships of War, Commanded by the brave Commodore Warren, afterwards made Knight of the Bath & Vice Admiral of the White." See Print No. 1098.
    - Print No. 986. Engraving: "Truxton's Victory.", undated (Folder FF-27)
      Engraving depicts the engagement between the United States Frigate Constellation of 36 guns, commanded by Capt. Truxton, and the French Fregate L'Insurgente of 40 guns, commanded by Capt. Bureaut, Feby. 9th, 1799. Published and sold by E. Pember and S. Luzerder, Philadelphia. Print is the same as No. 96. Full uncut margins. No Washington print is printed on the reverse side.
    - Print No. 991. Lithograph, colored: "The Sailor - Far-Far at Sea.", 1845 (Folder FF-27)
      Lithographed and published by N. Currier, New York. Eight lines of verse below title. Peters No. 1253.
    - Print No. 996. Engraving, colored: "[Engagement between the Serapis & Bon Homme Richard, Sept. 23, 1779]", 1781 (Folder FF-27)
      Engraved by John Peltro. Published Dec. 1, 1781, by John Harris, London. After painting by Richard Dodd. The Bon Homme Richard was under the command of John Paul Jones. Companion piece to Print No. 997.
    - Print No. 997. Engraving, colored: "View of his Majesty's ship Mediator attacking the enemy on 12 of December, 1782.", 1783 (Folder FF-27)
      Engraved by John Peltro after painting by Richard Dodd. Published, September 18, 1783, by John Harris, London. Depicts three French and two American vessels. Companion piece to Print No. 996 and duplicate of Print No. 354, except in colors.
    - Print No. 998. Aquatint, colored: "[The Phoenix and the Rose Engaged by the Enemy's Fire Ships and Galleys on the 16th of August 1776]", 1777 (Folder FF-27)
      Engraved by Dominic Serres. Published by J.F.W. Des Barres, London, 1777. Proof before printed title of the first state of this plate done for the Atlantic Neptune. Engraved from the original picture by D. Serres after sketch by Sir James Wallace. See No. 65 for second state showing the Palisades.
    - Print No. 999. Engraved map: "An Exact Plan of Charleston Bar and Harbour. From an Actual Survey.", 1791 (Folder FF-18)
      Full title: "An Exact Plan of Charleston Bar and Harbour. From an Actual Survey. With the Attack of Fort Sullivan, on the 28th of June 1776. By his Majestys Squadron, Commanded by Sir Peter Parker." Printed for Robert Sayer, London, 1791. Fortifications and locations of British and American forces, and warships indicated. Survey information of the harbor listed.
    - Print No. 1000. Engraved map, colored: "Attack of the Rebels upon Fort Penobscot...", 1785 (Folder FF-24)
      Full title: "Attack of the Rebels upon Fort Penobscot in the Province of New England in which their Fleet was totally destroyed and their Army dispersed the 14th. Augt. 1779. by an Officer present." Map of the portion of Penobscot River and Bay where the naval engagement took place. No engraver or publisher named. "For the Continuation (after Tindal's) of Rapin's History of Engd. publishd. as Act directs Decr. 18th, 1785." at center bottom. Similar to Print No. 934.
    - Print No. 1001. Aquatint: "Engagement between the American Frigate the Constitution, and the English Frigate the Guerriere, surrendered after having been entitely disabled.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Aquatint - blue tints. Title also in French. "Baugean del." "Jazet sculp." "Deposé". "A Paris chez Ostervald,... Rue de la Parcheminerie No. 2." Companion print to the aquatint of the engagement between the "Macedonian" and the "United States" by Baugean and Jazet. (Print No. 1002).
    - Print No. 1002. Aquatint: "Engagement between the American Frigate, The United States and the English Frigate the Macedonian surrended after 17 minutes of fighting.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Aquatint - blue tints. Title also in French. "Baugean del." "Jazet sculp." "Deposé". "A Paris chez Ostervald,... Rue de la Parcheminerie No. 2." Companion print to the aquatint of the engagement between the "Guerriere" and the "Constitution" by Baugean and Jazet. (Print No. 1001).
    - Print No. 1004. Lithograph, in sepia: "The Capture of H.B.M. Frigate Java; ...", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Full title: "The Capture of H.B.M. Frigate Java; by the U.S. Frigate Constitution, after an engagement of 1 hour & 55 minutes. American Loss 9 killed, 25 wounded, British Loss 60 killed, 170 wounded" No date or publisher given. May be a later state of Print No. 195.
    - Print No. 1005. Engraving: "Aqua Fortis.", 1815 (Folder FF-31)
      Trial proof before title, in black and white of the first of a pair of line engravings of the Battle of Lake Erie. "F. K___(unreadable; Kearny) del." "G. Murray fec't." Published July 25, 1815, at Philadelphia by Murray, Draper, Fairman & Co. and J. Webster. First state of completed print, Print No. 241.
    - Print No. 1010A. Engraving, colored: "Madisonville in Massachusetts bay - Essex & her Prizes.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Drawn by Capt. Porter. Engraved by W. Strickland. Illustrations from "Journal of a Cruise Made to the Pacific Ocean" by Captain Porter, N.Y., 1822.
    - Print No. 1010B. Engraving, colored: "The Victory.", undated (Folder FF-24)
    - Print No. 1010C. Engraving, colored: "Commodore Porter.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Engraved by Prud'homme after a painting by J. Wood. Second State.
    - Print No. 1013. Engraving, colored: "Columbia lamenting the loss of her Son...", 1800 (Folder FF-24)
      Full title: "Columbia lamenting the loss of her Son Who redeem'd her from Slav'ry & Liberty won While Fame is directed by Justice to spread The sad tidings afar that Washington's dead." Small oval portrait of George Washington is at the center of the print with figures of Columbia and Justice to the sides. No engraver named. Published by Pember & Luzarder, Philadelphia, 1800.
    - Print No. 1014. Aquatint, in black & white: "The U.S. Squadron, under Command of Com. Decatur, At anchor off the City of Algiers, June 30th 1815.", 1816 (Folder FF-24)
      Engraved by G. Munger & S.S. Jocelin. Published by N. Jocelin & G. Munger, New Haven, Feb. 1816. Same print as Print No. 657, except in black & white.
    - Print No. 1017. Engraved portrait: "Commre. O.H. Perry.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      No engraver or publisher given.
    - Print No. 1019. Aquatint, colored: "Frégate Américaine", 1824 (Folder FF-24)
      Engraved by C.F. Barallier. Drawn by Frederic Roux. Published "A Paris chez BULLA rue St. Jacques No. 38 et a Marseille chez Ruspini". At bottom right corner - "Déposé"
    - Print No. 1020. Aquatint, colored: "The United States Ship of the Line Pennsylvania leaving the Capes of the Delaware.", undated (Folder FF-31)
      Published by C.P. Fessenden, Philadelphia.
    - Print No. 1023. Aquatint in sepia: "His Majesty's Brig Penguin", 1805 (Folder FF-24)
      Aquatint - sepia tinted. "J.T. Serres del." "Clark & Harraden sculp." "Published & Sold March 1st. 1805 by Edwd. Orme, His Majesty's Printseller, 5g New Bond Street, London." Vignette.
    - Print No. 1024. Engraved map: "P of North America, New England, New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania.", circa 1729 (Folder FF-24)
      Engraved by Herman Moll, geographer. Description of postal service in lower right corner. Published about 1729.
    - Print No. 1025. Engraving: "Yale College.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Engraved by S.S. Jocelyn after painting by Henry C. Pratt. Published by N.& S.S. Jocelyn, N. Haven, Conn. Second State.
    - Print No. 1026. Aquatint, colored: "New Haven, Conn. Comprising a View of the Episcopal & Presbyterian Churches, State House & Yale College.", 1829 (Folder FF-31)
      Drawn, engraved and published by Illman & Pilbrow, New York, 4 Wall Street.. Engraved in part by John Hill.
    - Print No. 1027. Engraving, colored: "Nieu Amsterdam at New York.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Engraved by A. Meijer. "Carolus Allard excudit cum privilegio ordinum Hollandiae et Westfrisiae. [Amsterdam, c. 1710] From Carolus Allard's Orbis Habitabilis, Amsterdam, c. 1710. Date depicted: 1673. (Stokes, ICONOGRAPHY, v.1, pl. 14-b, & pp. 219-220). "79" in upper right corner.
    - Print No. 1031. Lithograph, colored: "The Farmer's Home - Winter.", 1863 (Folder FF-31)
      Painted by George Henry Durrie. Published by Currier & Ives, New York. Peters No. 2354.
    - Print No. 1034. Drawing, pen and ink: "Plan of the Attack on Platsburgh by Genl. Sir George Prevost and Capt. Downie of the Navy...", 1815 (Folder FF-31)
      Full title: "Plan of the Attack on Platsburgh by Genl. Sir George Prevost and Capt. Downie of the Navy. From a drawing by Brig. Genl. Macomb, and copied by Hardress Saunderson, Capt & D.A. 2nd MG." "Qr Ms Genls Office, 17 January 1815." References in key: A-F, No. 1-8. No scale.
    - Print No. 1035. Mezzotint portrait, colored: "Lt. Col. Tarleton.", 1782 (Folder FF-31)
      "Painted by Sir Joshua Reynolds...Engraved by J.R. Smith." Published in London by J.R. Smith on Oct. 11, 1782.
    - Print No. 1039. Aquatints, colored: 4 small aquatints entitled: "Victoire, sur Le Lac Erie" "Defense de Baltimore" "Victoire sur Le Lac Champlain" and "Prise de La Fregate Anglaise la Java", undated (Folder FF-24)
      No artist, engraver, publisher or date given.
    - Print No. 1040. Aquatint, colored: "The Capture of H B M Sloop of War Frolic, Capt. Whinyates,...", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Full title: "The Capture of H B M Sloop of War Frolic, Capt. Whinyates,by the U.S. Sloop of War Wasp, Capn. Jab. Jones, on the 18th. of Octr. 1812, after a close Action of 43 Minutes. Soon after the Frolic surrended both her Masts went by the Board. She had 6 Merchant Ships under her Convoy." Drawn & Engraved by F. Kearny, from a Sketch by Lieut. Claxton, of the Wasp. No publication date is given. Fourth State (?).
    - Print No. 1041. Engravings: Portrait Engraving of "Major Genl. Andrew Jackson." and engraving, colored: "Battle of New Orleans.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Pencil notations - on the front of portrait engraving - Bance, Paris (presumably the publisher). On the back of second engraving - "Colored by hand by Evelyn F. Olds in 1950." Drawn and engraved for "Jackson Wreath".
    - Print No. 1042. Engraved portrait, colored: "Paul Jones Americain", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Full title: "Captaine Commandant la Frégatte l'Alliance Celêbre par son intrepidite dans les Combats." No information given on engraver, publisher, or date. Faded writing on border of print. Probably issued in France in 1780. Same print as Print No. 744, except in colors.
    - Print No. 1043. Engraving and woodcut: Portrait Engraving of "Paul Jones The Founder of the American Navy." and woodcut, colored "Engagement between Bon Homme Richard and Serapis.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      No information as to engraver, publisher or date given Pencil note on back of second engraving, "Evelyn F. Olds colored this print in 1955. It had been partially colored before."
    - Print No. 1069. Lithograph, colored: "Enterprize and Boxer.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Lithographed and published by H.R. Robinson of New York and Washington, D.C. Wrapped with this print is a letter from Mrs. Electra Havemeyer Webb to Irving S. Olds, from whom this print was a gift.
    - Print No. 1074. Engraving printed on silk: "Elegy on the Death of James Lawrence, Esq., late Commander of the U.S. Frigate Chesapeake.", undated (Folder FF-24)
      Designed and engraved by A. Bowen. A. Bowen, printer. Elegy consists of 28 lines of poetry. Vignette of monument to Lawrence at the top. Silk has been cut.
    - Print No. 1075. Aquatint, colored: "Representation of the action off Mud Fort on the River Delaware...", 1787 (Folder FF-31)
      Action on October 22, 1777. William Elliott, del., engr., & publ.
    - Print No. 1076. Engraving, colored: "A perspective View of the loss of the U.S. Frigate Philadelphia ...", undated (Folder FF-31)
      Full title: "A perspective View of the loss of the U.S. Frigate Philadelphia in which is represented her relative position to the Tripolitan Gun-boats when during their furious attack upon her she was unable to get a single gun to bear upon them." Chs. Denoon del: Engraver and publisher not named. Rectangle. Same as Print No. 815 (in black and white). From the collection of Henry Graves, Jr.
    - Print No. 1077. Engraving, colored: "A View of Commodore Preble's Squadron whilst engaging the Gun-boats and Forts of Tripoli...", undated (Folder FF-31)
      Full title: "A View of Commodore Preble's Squadron whilst engaging the Gun-boats and Forts of Tripoli on the 3rd of August 1804 when they captured three of the Tripolitan Gun-boats & greatly damag'd the Bashaw's Fortifications." Chs. Denoon del: Engraver and publisher not named. Key to view is below title. Companion piece to Print No. 1076. From Collection of Henry Graves, Jr.
    - Print No. 1080. Mezzotint, colored: "This representation of the engagement between the United States Frigate Constitution and his Britannic Majesty's Frigate Guerriere,...", 1813 (Folder FF-32)
      Full title: "This representation of the engagement between the United States Frigate Constitution and his Britannic Majesty's Frigate Guerriere, which issued in the Capture and destruction of the Guerriere, on the 19th of August 1812, is respectfully dedicated to the President of the United States by the publishers Freeman and Pierie." Published at Philadelphia on the 8th day of March - 1813, by Freeman & Pierie of the State of Pennsylvania. Drawn by I. Hull. From the Collection of Henry Graves, Jr.
    - Print No. 1081. Engraving, colored: "United States and Macedonian...", 1817 (Folder FF-24)